Today's דף Daf is ק"ט, Kuf Tet, one or two. And we're
in the middle of an interesting discussion about whether משה Moshe was
a כהן Kohen or כהן גדול Kohen Gadol even. Interesting why the
גמרא Gemara jumps to the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol possibility, but anyway
the fact that he did the עבודה Avoda during the מילואים, Miluim,
does that demonstrate that he's a כהן? Kohen?
And this came through a discussion about the whole issue of an
אונן, Onen, and does an אונן Onen need קרבנות? Korbanot? Why did
they burn the חטאת Chatas on the eighth day of the מילואים?
Miluim? And one answer is because of אנינות, Aninus, and which is
the most obvious thing going on in the פסוקים Psukim there. And
then the question is, why not just get פנחס Pinchas to do
it? Well, פנחס Pinchas wasn't a כהן Kohen yet; he only became
a כהן Kohen later, even though he was a descendant of אהרן.
Aharon. The כהונה Kehuna status applied to אהרן Aharon and his four
children, not to the children they had that were already born. Why
not just give it to משה Moshe if משה Moshe was a
כהן? Kohen? And the answer is משה Moshe was too busy being
with God. But anyway, so that got us into this discussion,
was משה Moshe a כהן? Kohen? And what that really does is
it raises the
question that כהונה Kehuna is conceptually not about being—meaning it's a status
that doesn't start with the idea of being a descendant of אהרן,
Aharon, right?
מלכי צדק—no, Malki Tzedek that—מלכי צדק מלך שלם—no, Malki Tzedek Melech Shalem
not מלכי צדק, Malki Tzedek, but יתרו Yitro is כהן מדין, Kohen
Midian, okay? But isn't who else is a—והוא כהן לאל עליון, vehu
Kohen l'El Elyon, that's—yeah, that's מלכי צדק מלך שלם, Malki Tzedek Melech
Shalem, והוא כהן לאל עליון, vehu Kohen l'El Elyon, right? So the
idea that originally the כהונה Kehuna was with the
בכורים, Bechorim, was with the firstborn. It is a status
of a class of people that are designated
to serve God. And didn't say that you had to go to
כהונה Kehuna school like we go to rabbinical school, maybe there was
some sense of—so the children of אהרן Aharon is a hereditary way
of instantiating that. The idea of a בכור Bechor is another way
of instantiating that. Every generation has its כהנים, Kohanim, but it's not
like hereditary. Could be that somebody is מלכי צדק Malki Tzedek or
whatever, somebody's just recognized as a כהן. Kohen. Like now we have
somebody who goes through a training period or whatever, but who knows?
So כהונה Kehuna is not conceptually limited to the idea of the
sons of אהרן. Aharon. So what the גמרא Gemara is sort of
suggesting is that well, maybe it was sort of משה Moshe was
included in the class of כהנים Kohanim at that time. It just
didn't go onto his children, but maybe he was a כהן. Kohen.
So within this the גמרא Gemara is going to continue to explore
this. So we continue at the bottom of—oh, and the interesting, I
should say, right, the interesting other side of that coin is פנחס.
Pinchas. פנחס Pinchas was a descendant of אהרן Aharon and not a
כהן, Kohen, at least initially. And one
wonders if his other children had sons, right, and they were alive
at the time
that they became—that אהרן Aharon and his four sons became כהנים. Kohanim.
So maybe—and they never went and killed זמרי. Zimri. So it could
be that there were actually descendants of אהרן Aharon who are still
alive today, who lived in the time of the משכן Mishkan and
the בית ראשון Beit Rishon or whatever, who weren't כהנים Kohanim because
they were not part—weren't born after that כהונה Kehuna status was put
on—was sort of—not imposed, but imparted to אהרן Aharon and his four
sons. So you actually could have a non-כהן Kohen son of אהרן
Aharon who is a כהן—משה—and you can have a son of אהרן
Aharon in theory who's not a כהן—פנחס—and maybe who knows, maybe his
cousins or some others. Yes.
Yeah. Well, there's a מדרש Midrash that משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu had
a descendant who was a כהן Kohen to idols.
Yes. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So we're
going to see if משה Moshe was or was not a כהן.
Kohen מיתיבי, Meisivei, last line of ק"א עמוד ב'. Kuf Aleph Amud
Bet. I'll ask you. מרים מי הסגירה? Miriam mi hisgira? Who declared
מרים Miriam to be a מצורע Metzora and put her into her
צרעת Tzara'at status? Because you need a כהן Kohen to do it.
אם תאמר משה הסגירה, Im tomar Moshe hisgira, משה זר הוא. Moshe
zar hu. משה Moshe was a זר, zar, a non-כהן. Kohen. ואין
זר
רואה את הנגעים, v'ein zar ro'eh et hanega'im, and a non-כהן Kohen
could not do it. ואם תאמר אהרן הסגירה, v'im tomar Aharon hisgira,
אהרן קרוב
הוא. Aharon karov hu. He was a relative. ואין קרוב רואה את
הנגעים, v'ein karov ro'eh et hanega'im, and you can't have a relative
do it. Okay, so actually that's a debate,
whether and if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, this has got to
be one of the best lines in a משנה Mishnah ever. תוספות
Tosafot quotes the line—if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, פלוגתא היא, plugta
hi, תוספות Tosafot says אהרן קרוב הוא ואין קרוב רואה את הנגעים.
Aharon karov hu v'ein karov ro'eh et hanega'im. פלוגתא היא במסכת נגעים
פרק ב'. Plugta hi b'Masechet Negaim Perek Bet. תנן, Tnan, כל הנגעים
אדם רואה חוץ מנגעי עצמו. kol hanega'im adam ro'eh chutz minegei atzmo.
So you can see any נגעים, nega'im, you can make a—you can
judge any spot of צרעת tzara'at except you can't rule it for
yourself. But of course you just read that a little metaphorically: you
can see everybody else's blemishes except your own. We're always very quick
to see other people's problems. But anyway, according to the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, the only person excluded is yourself. רבי מאיר אומר אף
נגעי קרוביו, Rabbi Meir omer af negei krovav, even those of your
relatives. Okay, so this is assuming רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's position. ואם
תאמר אהרן הסגירה אהרן קרוב הוא ואין קרוב רואה את הנגעים. v'im
tomar Aharon hisgira Aharon karov hu v'ein karov ro'eh et hanega'im. Now
why didn't it have actually
that אלעזר Elazar did it? There—how broad does it think קרוב karov
is? You know, they're only nephews. They're not immediate קרובים. kerovim. So
maybe that's included in קרוב. karov. Not clear what the parameters are.
Maybe they figured that would not be כבוד. kavod. Like it's one
thing for an older brother to do it, right? It's another thing
for my nephew to rule on me, you know, that's not respectful
of Miriam. The גמרא Gemara though doesn't ask that question. Anyway it
says, so אלא כבוד גדול חלק הקדוש ברוך הוא למרים. Ella, kvod
gadol chalak haKadosh Baruch Hu leMiriam. God gave her great
honor in that hour. אני כהן, Ani kohen, it's as if God
was saying I'll be the כהן, Kohen. which is a little ironic,
you got to love it, it's sort of like God wearing תפילין,
tefillin, you know, I'm going to be the כהן, Kohen like a
כהן kohen, is somebody who serves God. But anyway, so ואני מסגירה
ואני פוטרה. va'ani masguira va'ani potrah. I will put her in her
status of being a
מצורע metzora and when her week is over, I will free her
from her status. So now, okay so that's quite fascinating. But you
know, but what's also fascinating is that, you know, sometimes even if
something bad is being said about you, there's a question about the
כבוד kavod in terms of who's the one that's saying it. If
somebody important, you know, has to be fired in the company, you
know, the, you know, whatever, the vice president or whatever, do you
send in some, you know, some, you know, do you have the
chairman of the board come and fire the person, you know, or
do you have some little functionary come and fire the person, right?
Or get it in an email, right, exactly.
So even if you're going to be making her into a מצורע,
metzora, who's going to be making her into a מצורע metzora is
a question of כבוד, kavod, okay? And that God will be exempting
her. But the idea of God being a כהן kohen, is just
a fascinating idea. Now here it's not a כהן kohen as if
God saying I'll be a כהן kohen in the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, right, that would be a little bit like to serve me,
here it's the other functions of a כהן, kohen which is actually
quite interesting if you think about it, right, because, you know, there's
a whole question, right, about are כהנים kohanim שלוחי דרחמנא shluchei deRachmana
or שלוחי דידן, shluchei didan, represent God or represent us or whatever,
you know, and but if you think about it when they're in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash they're primarily serving God. Out of the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right, whether if they're teaching תורה, Torah, which
is the one יורו משפטיך ליעקב, yoru mishpatecha leYaakov, right, before the
rabbis they were the תורה Torah teachers, right, you know, if they're
teaching תורה Torah or if they're doing this צרעת tzara'at function, right,
or if they're serving on a בית דין, beit din, which is
also in the תורה Torah they were the primary people before there
were rabbis to be on the בית דין, beit din, right, they're
more like seen as serving the people than they are serving God.
Serving the people as God's representatives, but serving the people, right? So
it's interesting, right, God can essentially be a כהן kohen in that
capacity, you know what I'm saying? Like bringing God's תורה Torah to
the people, God teaches us תורה Torah and the כהנים kohanim teach
us תורה, Torah, right? You know, so if the כהנים kohanim rule
on צרעת, tzara'at, you know, then God can rule on צרעת. tzara'at.
If the כהנים kohanim impart justice through a בית דין, beit din,
God can impart justice. So there's not a contradiction there to speak
about God in His capacity of a כהן. kohen, In the capacity
of a כהן kohen in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash would be
bizarre, but in the capacity of a כהן kohen. not serving in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash but serving the people, it's not so
bizarre. Okay, anyway so that's but what's relevant, so that's totally fascinating,
but what's relevant for us, קא תני מיהת, ka tani miat, the
גמרא Gemara says okay, okay, that's all fascinating, but bracket all of
that. What we get for our discussion is משה זר. Moshe zar.
It says that Moshe couldn't do it because he was a זר.
zar. ואין זר רואה את הנגעים, ve'ein zar roeh es hanega'im, and
a זר zar cannot see the נגעים. nega'im. So you see that
Moshe was a זר. zar. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, שאני מראות נגעים דאהרן ובניו כתובין בפרשה. shani mar'os
nega'im de-Aharon u-vanav ketuvim be-parsha. No, by the מראות נגעים mar'os nega'im
it doesn't just say הכהן, ha-kohen, it says והובא אל אהרן הכהן
או אל אחד מבניו הכהנים. ve-huva el Aharon ha-kohen o el achad
mi-banav ha-kohanim. It explicitly says אהרן Aharon and one of his children,
so there it's not enough to be a כהן, kohen you have
to be a כהן kohen who also is a descendant of אהרן.
Aharon. Now of course the problem is that God also isn't in
that category, but okay we're going to bracket that. Okay so until
now we've been saying you can have a descendant of אהרן, Aharon,
פנחס, Pinchas who's not a כהן. kohen, You can have a כהן
kohen who's not a descendant of אהרן. Aharon. By נגעים nega'im for
some reason you דווקא davka need both. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara continues. מיתיבי. Mesivei. Okay, I'll ask you. Although the evidence is
stacking up that Moshe was not a כהן. kohen. Okay, but we're
going to challenge it again. חמש שמחות היתה אלישבע יתירה על בנות
ישראל. Chamesh smachot hitsah Elisheva yeseirah al bnot Yisrael. This is in
סדר עולם Seder Olam and it's talking about the day that the
משכן Mishkan was
dedicated or whatever.
And so אלישבע Elisheva is, you know, בת עמינדב אחות נחשון. bat
Amminadav achos Nachshon. She was נחשון Nachshon's sister and אהרן Aharon's wife.
So she had so many ways in which she was, five ways
in which she was joyous more than any other woman. Okay.
יבמה, Yevamah, her
brother-in-law, מלך, melech, was a king. משה Moshe was her brother-in-law, אהרן
Aharon's brother, he was the political leader of the people.
אישה, Ishah, her husband, כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. בנה, Binah, her one
of her sons, סגן, sgan, אלעזר Elazar was the vice כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. Okay, בן בנה, Ben binah, her grandson, משוח מלחמה, Mashuach
Milchamah, her grandson פנחס Pinchas, was the one who was going to
lead them to war. This obviously assumes that פנחס Pinchas had his
status
as
a כהן kohen well before the זמרי Zimri event. And not only
did he have a status as a כהן, kohen. the idea that
he would also be the one to lead them to war, although
that only happened later with the whole... with the whole בנות מדין
Bnot Midian story and so on, presumably that was already designated at
this point. So that's a little reading the future into... into the
story. Okay? ואחיה נשיא שבט Ve-achia Nasi Shevet
and her brother נחשון Nachshon was the head of a tribe. So
look at all this יחוס yichus she had. Of course, this is
a complete patriarchy because all of her שמחה simcha was about all
of the ways that her male relatives, right, had all of this
status.
She was related to מרים Miriam too.
Well, that's true too. Anyway, and nevertheless, or consider that at the
height of this שמחה, simcha, okay, I'm not exactly sure why the
height of this שמחה simcha is the day the משכן Mishkan was
dedicated, maybe that's because you know, at least her husband and her
sons and their status had been confirmed also on the eighth day
of the מילואים, Miluim, right, because the מילואים Miluim process was not
just dedicating the משכן, Mishkan, it was dedicating the כהנים Kohanim as
well, you know. And nevertheless, at this day at the height of
her שמחה, simcha, ואבילות על שני בניה, ve-aveilut al shnei vaneha, she
became an אבילה aveila on two of her sons נדב ואביהוא, Nadav
ve-Avihu, so the poignancy of the tragedy. One minute, okay. קתני מיהת,
Katani mihat, anyway, nevertheless, what we step back to teach us is
יבמה מלך, Yevamah Melech, her brother-in-law was a king. מלך הן כהן
גדול הן, Melech hen Kohen Gadol hen, just a king. Was she
mentioning all the ways she was joyous, mentioned that her brother-in-law was
also a כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? אמה אף מלך, Eima af melech,
no no, we're going to get to the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
by her husband, so it doesn't mean to exclude that possibility from
משה. Moshe That's true, of all the proofs, that was the weakest.
But nevertheless, all the evidence is seeming to point to the fact
that משה Moshe. was not being recognized as a כהן. kohen Yes,
Charlie.
משוח מלחמה Mashuach Milchama is a כהן.
Kohen, Yes,
I said that. Yeah, yeah, I said that that goes against the
previous discussion.
I know, I said that. This goes against that earlier discussion. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says כתנאי. Katannai. Keep up, Charlie. Okay, כתנאי.
Katannai. Okay,
so this is so this question actually we're going to concede, I
mean, there's been pretty good evidence to it, so we're going to
see that this question of is משה כהן Moshe Kohen is a
debate of תנאים. Tannaim. ויחר אף ה' במשה. Vayichar af Hashem be-Moshe.
When משה Moshe kept on complaining, you know, oh, you know, send
somebody else, right? And then he says and God got angry at
משה Moshe and said הנה אהרן אחיך הלוי, Hinei Aharon achicha ha-Levi,
fine, אהרן, Aharon, your brother is coming to meet you, he'll speak
for you. רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer,
כל חרון אף שבטורה נאמר בו רושם. kol charon af she-ba-Torah ne'emar
bo roshem. Whenever it says God's anger was, you know, burned against
a person, it always means that there was some way or anybody's
anger burned against a person, it always leaves a mark. And רש"י
Rashi says a mark doesn't have to be a physical mark. Sometimes
it could be a mark is that somebody like, you know, castigates
you and yells at you and whatever and the mark is like,
you know, being publicly, you know, criticized or whatever. But there's some
consequence to it. It's not just the anger burns up inside. Okay,
the anger is directed at you and somehow that's felt, there's an
impact of that anger. I believe
that I was trying to remember last night, I once had a
conversation with נחום סרנא Nachum Sarna עליו השלום alav ha-shalom about this,
and I think the question is whether it's ויחר אף במשה, Vayichar
af be-Moshe, 'be', or ויחר אף. Vayichar af. ויחר אף Vayichar af
just means the anger was, you know, the person's anger was burning
up, but 'be', against a person, means that there actually was some
impact. By the way, just the words חרון אף, charon af, it's
worth knowing what those words mean. Right, אף af is the nose.
Okay, and like ויחר אף vayichar af basically means like smoke is
coming out of the nostrils. If you have that image, right? So
like so the fiery nostrils, almost like smoke is coming out of
somebody's nostrils, and 'be' is like, you know, directed at somebody. Okay,
so רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, כל חרון אף
שבטורה נאמר בו רושם וזה לא נאמר בו רושם. kol charon af
she-ba-Torah ne'emar bo roshem ve-zeh lo ne'emar bo roshem. But here it
just says God got angry at משה Moshe and then said oh,
אהרן Aharon is going to speak for you. It seems like God
conceded to משה's Moshe request. Where is the consequence? Where is the
impact of God's anger? רבי שמעון בן יוחי אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai omer, אף זה נאמר בו רושם. af zeh ne'emar bo roshem.
No, the impact of this was felt as well. שנאמר הלא אהרן
אחיך הלוי. She-ne'emar halo Aharon achicha ha-Levi. Okay, הלא אהרן אחיך הלוי,
Halo Aharon achicha ha-Levi, ולא כהן הוא? ve-lo Kohen hu? Wasn't he
a כהן? Kohen. Which raises interesting questions, right? When exactly was the
כהונה kehunah status recognized and given, right? I mean, it seems like
it was all given like that was the whole process of the
whole מילואים Miluim period. Okay, so anyway, so this is interesting imagining
that the כהונה kehunah status in theory existed earlier. So or at
least it's saying why are you calling him a לוי, Levi, we
know he's going to be a כהן. Kohen. Anyway, הכי קאמר, hachi
ka-amar, here's what it means. אני אמרתי אתה כהן והוא לוי. Ani
amarti attah Kohen ve-hu Levi. My plan had been that you, משה,
Moshe would be both the king and the כהן, Kohen? which as
we know has been not a good idea to combine religious leadership
together with political leadership. Okay, just look at the חנוכה Chanukah story,
just look at the State of Israel. Anyway, so okay, well also,
anyway, I was going to combine the two. עכשיו, Achshav, now that
you are דרייען מיר א קאפ drayen mir a kop so much,
and you're making so much trouble, עכשיו... achshav... כהן ואתה לוי. kohen
veatah levi. So he was אהרן אחיך הלוי, Aharon achicha halevi, it's
a little ironic because it's actually saying he was supposed to be
the לוי, Levi, but now because of this, you know, like it's
emphasizing his status to sort of say this was what was going
to be, a funny read of the פסוק pasuk anyway, but no,
he's going to now be the כהן, Kohen. you'll be the לוי.
Levi. Okay, which basically means that משה Moshe, never got a status
of being a כהן. Kohen, וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim, and the חכמים
chachamim say לא נתכהן משה אלא שבעת ימי המילואים בלבד. lo nitkahen
Moshe ela shivat yemei hamiluim bilvad. He was only during those seven
days of the מילואים, miluim, which is like how's that different? It
says he wasn't a כהן. kohen, So רש״י Rashi says the difference
is that according to this, that was never the plan. They don't
agree with this read. It wasn't like he was supposed to be
the כהן kohen. and then it got removed from him. You know,
no, the plan never had been for him to be a כהן.
kohen. The plan had always just for him to be to serve
in these seven days of the מילואים. miluim. But one way or
the other they're agreeing he wasn't a כהן. kohen Now, ויש אומרים
veyesh omrim and for the
first opinion was saying he wasn't a כהן kohen. during those seven...
No, that's what I'm saying, he was. It's just that the plan
had been, the question was, do they agree that the plan had
been for him to be a כהן kohen. and it was removed,
or that never been the plan? But they both agree that he
served as a כהן kohen for those seven days.
As a כהן גדול kohen gadol also?
Yeah, I don't know, I don't know why the גמרא Gemara insists
on the גדול gadol point, like since when do we have two
כהנים גדולים? kohanim gedolim? ויש אומרים, veyesh omrim, but maybe it's just
can't say, anyway once you're making him a כהן kohen you can't
have him not be a כהן גדול kohen gadol I guess is
the point. ויש אומרים veyesh omrim and some say, and this is
the position of רבי Rebbi that we were saying before, that he,
was it רבי? Rebbi? Whoever it was that was saying that he
was a כהן. kohen ויש אומרים, veyesh omrim, no, not רבי, Rebbi,
who was it?
רב. Rav. Okay, ויש אומרים, veyesh omrim, so רב Rav is going
like the ויש אומרים. veyesh omrim. לא פסקא כהונה אלא מזרעו של
משה. lo paska kehuna ela mizaro shel Moshe. No, משה Moshe was
a כהן. kohen It's just that that כהונה kehuna was not given
to continue with his children, okay? But the כהונה kehuna status was
imparted to אהרן, Aharon, his children, and אהרן׳ס Aharon's children's children, and
to משה, Moshe but not to משה׳ס Moshe's children. שנאמר, shenemar, ומשה
איש האלהים בניו יקראו על שבט הלוי. u-Moshe ish ha-elohim banav yikare'u
al shevet ha-levi. משה, Moshe, the man of God, his children are
attributed to the tribe of לוי. Levi. But משה Moshe, is not
seen as a לוי, Levi, משה Moshe the way this פסוק pasuk
is being read is a כהן. kohen. Okay? But it was just
a כהונה kehuna that did not pass on to the children. ואומר,
ve'omer, and the verse says, משה ואהרן בכהניו ושמואל בקוראי שמו. Moshe
ve-Aharon be-kohannav u-Shmuel be-korei shemo. Okay, so משה Moshe and אהרן Aharon
in their כהונה kehuna status. So it sounds like reading that
בכהניו be-kohannav not just as,
you know, you could say that בכהנו be-kohano refers to משה Moshe
if you really want to parse that out.
Yes, we are reading it with this בכהניו. be-kohannav. Oh, משה כמה?
Moshe kama? I don't think that's פשט. pshat. Okay, so but the
פשט pshat more of course בכהניו be-kohannav means, oh I see, כהנו
kohano is singular? Interesting,
interesting. Anyway, but even so you could read כהונה kehuna status as
like service, you know,
as opposed to literally כהן kohen. in the, you know, in this
sort of in this way. But yes, good point, כהנו kohano is
singular. I hear your point, I hear your point. Okay, מאי ואומר?
mai ve'omer? Why did you need another פסוק? pasuk? Didn't you have
the פסוק pasuk about בניו יקראו על שבט הלוי? banav yikare'u al
shevet ha-levi? וכי תימא, vechi tema, לדורות הוא דכתיב. ledorot hu de-chtiv.
No, the reason it says his children is because the purpose of
that פסוק pasuk משה איש האלהים Moshe ish ha-elohim in דברי הימים
Divrei Ha-yamim is to speak about what was the story because משה
Moshe was already dead, it was to speak about the story of
the later generations. So its focus was the later generations but it
didn't mean to imply that משה Moshe wasn't a לוי. Levi. ואומר,
ve'omer, so משה ואהרן בכהניו, Moshe ve-Aharon be-kohannav, fine, so I'll show
you a פסוק pasuk that makes it clear that משה Moshe was
a כהן, kohen. bracketing Michael's critique. Okay now, so anyway, so there
you see it was a debate was משה Moshe a כהן kohen
or not. Now we're going to talk about different things that came
up in that discussion. Okay, so it says, מאי, mai, וכל חרון
אף שבתורה נאמר בו רושם? vechol charon af she-ba-Torah ne'emar bo roshem?
Every time it says fire anger, it leaves a mark? והכתיב, vehachtiv,
ויצא מעם פרעה בחרי אף? vayetze me'im Paroh bechari af? משה Moshe
left פרעה Paroh in fiery anger. Now again, the point I made
before, there's no, well but yeah, but not that anger did not
itself, מכת בכורות makat bechorot was going to happen anyway, that act
of being angry at פרעה Paroh did not leave a mark. Although
again, the point I made is that there's no ויחר אף בפרעה,
vayichar af be-Paroh, it just says בחרי אף, bechari af, right? But
the גמרא Gemara is not paying attention to the ב bet issue
because the statement was any חרון אף charon af leaves a mark.
So they're saying where's the mark here? ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי.
velo amar leh velo midi. He didn't even publicly castigate him. So
at least the mark, again, doesn't have to be a physical mark,
but some sense of some directing of that anger towards him.
פרעה Paroh had more power.
I understand,
nobody is critiquing משה, Moshe the point is is that don't make
a claim that the word חרון אף charon af always means that
that anger was not just burning inside but the anger somehow was
directed and impacted the other person.
When someone's more powerful has the חרון אף?
charon af? It doesn't matter, if the description of the word means,
you know, that the anger hit out against a person, so where
is that hitting out that occurred? Okay, so אמר ריש לקיש, amar
Resh Lakish, סטרו. setaro.
No, he slapped פרעה Paroh in the face. That wasn't mentioned in
the פסוק, pasuk, that's, but you're right, the חרון אף charon af
means it was acted on, so he slapped him in the face
ויצא vayetze and he left. ומי אמר ריש לקיש הכי? umi amar
Resh Lakish hachi? Did ריש לקיש Resh Lakish say that משה Moshe,
would actually slap Pharaoh in the face? והכתיב *V'hachtiv*: ונצבת לקראתו על
שפת היאור *v'nitzavta likraso al sfat hay'or*, you'll stand to greet פרעה
*Paro* by the river, that's earlier obviously in the story. ואמר ריש
לקיש *V'amar Resh Lakish*: מלך הוא *melech hu*, והסבר לו פנים *v'hasber
lo panim*, what it means to stand up in front of him
means that he's still a king and even though you're going to
be locked in battle with him, show him due respect, present yourself
in a way of respect. רבי יוחנן אמר amar, *Rabbi Yochanan amar*
no, רשע הוא *rasha hu* והעז פניך בו *v'ha-ez panecha bo*. No,
ונצבת *v'nitzavta* means like you know, דתן ואבירם יצאו נצבים *Dathan v'Aviram
yatzi nitzavim*. Right? ונצבת *Nitzavta* means like confront him, show him disrespect.
Okay.
יצאו נצבים היום *yatzi nitzavim hayom*.
Okay, so it could read either way. So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
is reading this as, you know, do it in an aggressive way.
So you see ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* would not say that משה
Moshe *Moshe* slapped פרעה *Paro*. So איפכא *ipucha* find, reverse it. Have
it be that ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* said show him, you know,
disrespect and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said show him, you know, respect.
And that's interesting. That's not saying then the חרון אף *charon af*
per se is what does it in metaphysically, it's saying the you
acting in your חרון אף *charon af*.
Yeah, we're not talking about metaphysically.
These are emotions. Right. It's not the חרון אף *charon af* per
se.
Correct. The description of the verse of using the verb ויחר אף
*vayichar af* is a way of
saying fiery angry and he lashed
and it had, you know, it's a description. It's a way of
describing the events. It's not just saying the anger by itself creates
a it's not a metaphysical statement. Yeah, yeah, yeah. No, it's saying
this is what the verb means. ויחר *Vayichar*... but again, if you
say ויחר אף ב *vayichar af be*, you understand it. Right? Anger,
he was fiery angry against him, right, then means but the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is dropping the focus on the ב *be*. Okay. Anyway,
אמר amar רבי ינאי *Amar Rabbi Yannai*: לעולם תהא אימת מלכות עליך
*l'olam t'he emat malchus alecha*. The fear of the king should always
be upon you even if it's a bad you have a bad
king. דכתיב *Dichtiv* or וירדו *v'yerdu*... now of course fear is not
the same as respect. Okay. וירדו כל עבדיך אלה אלי *v'yerdu kol
avadecha eleh elai*, all your servants will come down to me, said
משה Moshe. *Moshe* to פרעה *Paro*. But of course פרעה *Paro* is
the one who's going to come down to משה Moshe's *Moshe* and
say get out of here. ואילו לדידי לא קאמר ליה *V'eilu l'didi
lo ka'amar leh* but he didn't say you'll come down to me,
so he showed him respect. Now respect again, sometimes you show respect
because you have fear and you don't want to speak disrespectfully because
the consequence of speaking disrespectfully as opposed to genuinely showing respect. So
it is different, the question about whether, you know, if the person
has this position, you have to treat them with respect because, you
know, the position demands respect, or, you know, or even if, you
know, you think God is behind you and God is going to
bring the ten plagues, you should always have a fear of kings
the fear versus respect are not exactly the same thing even though
here they might express itself in the same way.
רבי יוחנן אמר מהכא *Rabbi Yochanan amar me-hacha*: ויד ה'
הייתה אל אליהו וישנס *v'yad
Hashem hayta el Eliyahu v'yeshannes* is
it וישנס *v'yeshannes* or
וישנס *v'yeshannes*? I think it's וישנס *v'yeshannes*. וישנס מתניו *V'yeshannes motnav*... וירץ
לפני אחאב *v'yaratz lifnei Achav*. So אחאב *Achav*...
so God was with אליהו *Eliyahu* and he like girded his loins
and he ran in front of אחאב *Achav*. So he sort of
showed respect that he was actually running in front, he was like
the, you know, that messenger that goes in front of the king.
So he was actually putting himself at that secondary position even though
obviously his whole position was to be critical of אחאב *Achav* and
so on. So that actually again is a real show of respect,
not just an expression of being a fear. אמר עולא *Amar Ulla*:
ביקש משה Moshe's מלכות ולא v'lo, ניתנו לו *bikesh Moshe malchus v'lo
nitnu lo*. משה *Moshe* actually wanted to be king. Now it's funny,
a minute ago we said he was king. So we're going to
see that what king means is that the kingship would be a
hereditary position for משה *Moshe*. Okay? And it wasn't given to him.
Okay? Because once we're going to use the phrase king, which obviously
is, you know, is anachronistic, right? The whole point is that the
king came much later, right? You know, if you're going to say
אשימה עלי מלך *asima alai melech* etc., the idea of kingship and
a, you know, and hereditary position, earlier it was the שופטים *shoftim*,
it wasn't it wasn't yet that model. You know, it's like the
Romans, right? You know, they never wanted to have a king, so
even when they had like emperors, they didn't want to call him
king. But they went a whole long period where, you know, where
it's like, you know, because of this whole thing with what was
it? the Rape of the Sabine women or whatever anyway, this whole
thing where the kingship was like a was like a taboo thing
for them. So, you know, so here too, like it's because the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* chose to use the word king earlier when it
was really describing the political leader. Okay. So anyway, so now we're
saying he wanted to be king, what we mean is what kingship
really is, not just a political leader but, you know, the status
and whatever, the trappings, and of course specifically also the hereditary aspect
of it. Okay. So משה *Moshe* wanted to
be king for himself and his kids? Or just really for his
kids?
No, well, the נפקא מינה *na fka mina* would be his kids
it seems. Okay. ולא ניתנו *V'lo nistan* but maybe, I don't know,
maybe for himself, maybe with all of the trappings. I mean, again,
it's interesting we don't normally assume that משה *Moshe*, ענו מאד *anav
me'od*. Right. Anyway, okay. ביקש משה מלכות ולא ניתנו לו *Bikesh Moshe
malchus v'lo nistan lo*. It wasn't given to him. דכתיב *Dichtiv*: אל
תקרב הלום halom *al tikrav halom*. When he's over there by the
סנה Sneh *sneh*, do not run na. ואין הלום halom אלא מלכות.
הלום halom, means kingdom, kingship, שנאמר, shene'emar, מי אנוכי ה' אלוקים, Mi
anochi Hashem Elokim, this is by דוד, David, who אמר, מי אנוכי
ה' אלוקים, Mi anochi Hashem Elokim, כי הביאתני עד הלום, ki heviatani
ad halom, that you've brought me until this place. So this place
is a place of like high status. So whereas in the סנה
Sneh, we assume that high status is the closeness to God and
being with the סנה, but by the גזירה שוה gezeira shava by
the use of the word, we're sort of saying that no, it's
a status of kingship.
מתיב רבא, Masiv Rava, so רבא Rava challenged, רבי ישמעאל אומר יבמה
מלך. Rabbi Yishmael omer yibamah melech. We said before that her brother-in-law,
אלעזר, Elazar, was a king. So you use the word king to
describe משה. אמר רבא לא לזרעו קאמר. Amar Rava lo l'zaro kama.
No, no, no, what we mean is the kingship that would be
a hereditary position, that's what he wanted. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, וכל היכא דכתיב הלום לדורות הוא? vechol heicha d'chsiv halom ledoros
hu? So you're saying הלום halom doesn't just mean kingship, it means
a kingship for future generations, okay, like a full kingship that will
pass down hereditary. והא גבי שאול דכתיב, Ve'ha gabi Shaul d'chsiv, but
by שאול Shaul it says הלום, halom and we know that didn't
go to his kids.
הבא עוד הלום איש, Haveh od halom ish, bring until this place
the man. Now
who is that, שמואל Shmuel says when they're going to anoint שאול.
Shaul. So it is interesting about another הלום being used to a
sense of being, you know, pointing someone as king. So הוא אין
זרעו לא, hu in zaro lo, but we know it only applied
to him, not to his future descendants. אי בעית אימא הוא הוי
איש בשת. I ba'is eima hu havai Ish-Bosheth. First of all, his
son at least was king, איש בשת Ish-Bosheth was king, even if
it was only for a very brief period of time. ואי בעית
אימא Ve'i ba'is eima if you want, שאני שאול דאפילו בגוויה לא
קיים. shani Shaul d'afilu begavei lo kayam. No, no, and שאול, Shaul,
it was supposed to be hereditary, but it got ripped away from
him. So, you know, so the point was was that like even
for him the kingship was what what he was given was taken
away, but what he was given was a hereditary kingship. Okay, כדרבי
אלעזר אמר רבי חנינא בשעה שפוסקין גדולה לאדם, k'deRabbi Elazar amar Rabbi
Chanina besha'ah sheposkin gedulah l'adam,
when it is decreed from up high that a person will get
a position of status, of importance, פוסקין לו ולזרעו עד סוף כל
הדורות, poskin lo u'lezaro ad sof kol hadoros, then it's not just
for you, it's for all future generations. (What about משה's children? Yeah,
that's a good question.) שנאמר לא יגרע מצדיק עיניו ואת מלכים לכסא,
Shene'emar lo yigra mi-tzaddik einav v'es melachim l'kise,
it will not be held back, you know, from a righteous person
what he desires and from kings from the throne. ואם הגיס
דעתו הקדוש ברוך הוא משפילו. Ve'im higis da'ato Hakadosh Baruch Hu mashpilo.
He, you know, just because you were given it doesn't mean that
you're going to keep it. Okay, if you become too haughty, then
God will strip it away from him. Yeah, Michael asks a good
question about משה's kids. שנאמר ואם אסורים בזיקים ילכדון בחבלי עוני. Shene'emar
ve'im asurim bazikkim yilachdun bechevlei oni. And if they're bound up with
like, you know, with ropes, they will be trapped with the, you
know, with the ropes of poverty, meaning so if they if they
become I don't know how how bound with ropes means that they're
that they're haughty, but anyway, if they take too much, you know,
pride in or whatever, it'll be stripped away from them. So but
yes, הלום does mean kingship for future generations, yes.
There are many prominent monarchs whose descendants' lines died out. Yes, so
this...
there you go. Okay, בעלי מומים. ba'alim u'mumin. Now we move on,
that was a fun אגדתא. aggadata. Now we move on to the
משנה. Mishnah. And the משנה Mishnah says that this idea that a
בעל מום ba'al mum doesn't do the עבודה, avodah, whether it... but
does get a portion in the sacrifices, whether it is a permanent
בעל מום ba'al mum or a temporary בעל מום. ba'al mum. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מנא הני מילי, minani
milei, where do you know this from? דתנו רבנן, D'tannu Rabbanan, we
taught: כל זכר בכהנים יאכל
אותה. kol zachar bakohanim yochal osah. That's now this פסוק pasuk all
males eat it, it says this by the מנחה, minchah, it says
this by the חטאת, chatas, and by a שלמים. shelamim. Every time
it says it, it's come coming to include a בעל מום. ba'al
mum. Okay, כל זכר, kol zachar, all males, and it's going to
include three types of בעלי מומים ba'alim mumin because it says it
three times. כל זכר לרבות בעלי מומים. Kol zachar lerabbos ba'alim mumin.
To include even a בעל מום. ba'al mum. Now למאי, lemai, what
are you including them for? אי לאכילה הא כבר נאמר לחם אלהיו
מקדשי הקדשים ומן הקדשים יאכל. I l'achilah ha kvar ne'emar lechem elohav
mikodesh hakodashim u'min hakodashim yochel. It's explicit in the תורה Torah that
a בעל מום ba'al mum eats from קרבנות. korbanos. So why you
don't have to say כל זכר kol zachar means they eat, okay,
and we rather, and we've seen this earlier, it means they're entitled
to eat, that they get a portion, not that they're permitted to
eat. אלא לחלוקה, Ella lachaluukah, it means that they're entitled and they
get a portion and the כל זכר kol zachar includes even a
בעל מום ba'al mum gets a portion. Okay, תניא אידך, tanya idach,
another ברייתא braisa taught: כל זכר לרבות בעלי מומים. kol zachar lerabbos
ba'alim mumin. To include בעלי מומים. ba'alim mumin. למאי, Lemai, what purpose?
אי לאכילה הא כבר נאמר, אי לחלוקה הא כבר נאמר. I l'achilah
ha kvar ne'emar, i lachaluukah ha kvar ne'emar.
We've already used another פסוק pasuk to say they get a portion.
What do you need another כל זכר? kol zachar? So שיאכל אין
לי אלא תם ונעשה בעל מום. sheyochel ein li ella tam bena'aseh
ba'al mum. So to include a... everybody who's in the בעל מום
ba'al mum category. I might have thought maybe it's somebody who was
born without a blemish and then got a blemish. Maybe that person
started in the category, so they continue to get a portion. Okay,
בעל מום מעיקרא מנא לן, ba'al mum me'ikara minayin, how do you
know somebody who started with a מום? mum? תלמוד לומר כל זכר,
Talmud lomar kol zachar, every male. Okay, that's a second כל זכר,
kol zachar, even born with a מום. mum. תניא אידך, Tanya idach,
third ברייתא braisa says: כל זכר. kol zachar. It says it a
third time. לרבות בעל מום. Lerabbos ba'al mum. למאי? Lemai? אי לאכילה
הא כבר נאמר, ואי לחלוקה הא כבר נאמר. I l'achilah ha kvar
ne'emar, ve'i lachaluukah ha kvar ne'emar. Okay, so fine, if it's for...
if it's to allow to eat, that's an explicit פסוק. pasuk. If
it's to give them a portion, we have two כל זכר kol
zachars already to give them a portion. ואיהו בעל מום מעיקרא הא
כבר נאמר. V'ihu ba'al mum me'ikara ha kvar ne'emar. to say to
include somebody who was born with a מום, mum, we already included
that. What do you need the third כל זכר kol zachar for?
יכול אין לי אלא בעל מום קבוע, yachol ein lee ela baal
mum kavua, בעל מום עובר מנין? baal mum over minayin? I only
know for a permanent blemish. How do I know even a temporary
blemish gets a portion? תלמוד לומר כל זכר, talmud lomar kol zachar,
all males. So now the גמרא Gemara says כלפי לייא? k'lapei laya?
כלפי לייא k'lapei laya means like which way is this going? It's
the opposite makes sense. Obviously you'd more be inclined to say a
temporary blemish gets a portion. Why do you need a פסוק pasuk
to include a temporary blemish? You should need a פסוק pasuk to
include a permanent blemish. So אמר רב ששת איפוך, amar Rav Sheshes
eipoch, fine you're right, reverse it. The god, you know, it means
I only know a temporary, how do I know a permanent? רב
אשי אמר לעולם לא תיפוך, Rav Ashi amar l'olam lo teipoch, don't
reverse it. You might have thought that a temporary blemish maybe doesn't
get a portion. Why? איצטריך, iztreech, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina,
I would have thought top of ק"ט עמוד ב'. kuf-tes amud beis.
כי טמא, ki tamei, maybe treat a temporary blemish like somebody who
is טמא. tamei. מה טמא כמאן דלא טהור לא אכיל, ma tamei
kamadu lo tahor lo achil, since טמא tamei is only a temporary
status, we say wait till that status goes away and then you'll
get your portion, אף האי נמי כמאן דלא מתקן לא אכיל. af
hai nami kamadu lo misaken lo achil. Here too, maybe as רש"י
Rashi says, תורה Torah is, you know, is more wants to be
more, you know, sensitive or responsive to the status of a כהן
kohen, with a permanent blemish who will always be excluded. Somebody who
maybe only has a temporary blemish and once the blemish goes away
will get a portion, maybe we shouldn't make an exception for him
and maybe we should say he doesn't get a portion just, you
know, for this period that he has the temporary blemish. So קא
משמע לן kamashmalan that no, that even he gets a portion even
though it's only temporary, okay, which again raises the question, how much
is this an exception? Or and then you could sort of say
maybe we shouldn't make an exception for everybody or how much is
it the rule because you'll remember the question is what is the
rule and this is exactly what the גמרא's Gemara going to look
at. Is the rule if you couldn't do the עבודה avoda you
shouldn't be getting a portion and that's why the and then the
בעל מום baal mum would be an exception to that rule? Or
is the rule if you weren't able to eat you don't get
a portion and read that way the בעל מום baal mum isn't
an exception? So remember we had those two models before and the
גמרא's Gemara going to revisit it right now. Okay, because כל שאינו
ראוי, kol she'eino rauy, so the משנה mishna says anybody who's not
fit to do the עבודה avoda doesn't get a portion.
ולא, is that really true? והרי בעל מום דלא ראוי לעבודה וחולק,
v'harei baal mum d'lo rauy l'avoda v'cholek, okay, a בעל מום baal
mum is fit for the עבודה, avoda, not fit for the עבודה
avoda and he gets a
portion, okay, ותו הראוי לעבודה חולק, v'su harauy l'avoda cholek, so the
implication of the משנה mishna is if you're fit for the עבודה
avoda you do get a portion, right? Because it says if you're
not fit you don't, presumably if you are fit you do. הרי
טמא בקרבנות ציבור, harei tamei b'korbanos tzibur, how about somebody who's טמא
tamei with a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, we also held and if
a כהן גדול kohen gadol is an אונן, onen, we had cases
where a person could do the עבודה avoda and doesn't get a
portion because they still can't eat.
ראוי לעבודה ואינו חולק. rauy l'avoda v'eino cholek. Okay, so you see
we have exceptions in both directions, okay. The בעל מום baal mum
can't do the עבודה avoda and gets a portion. Somebody who's טמא
tamei for a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur can do the עבודה avoda
and doesn't get a portion. So your rule fails, it's not about
being able to do the עבודה. avoda. So the גמרא Gemara says
fine, ראוי לאכילה קאמר, rauy l'achila ka'amar, which is what we said
earlier. You're right, that's really not the rule. The rule really is
not whether you can do the עבודה, avoda, the rule really is
whether you are able to eat. And that fits. A בעל מום
baal mum can eat, so he does get the portion, and it's
all about eating anyway. And the and the טמא tamei for קרבנות
ציבור korbanos tzibur and כהן גדול אונן kohen gadol onen can't eat
and they don't get a portion. Oh, it's all beautiful, except it's
not all beautiful because we have another even within the eating rule
we have an exception. והרי קטן, v'harei katan, how about a minor?
דראוי לאכילה, d'rauy l'achila, a minor can eat, ואינו חולק, v'eino cholek,
he doesn't get a portion because the פסוק pasuk says איש כאחיו,
ish k'achiv, and from there we learn that it means only an
איש, ish, and we also learn that a קטן katan can't do
the עבודה. avoda. So by a קטן, katan, the עבודה avoda rule
works, but the eating rule doesn't work. Got it? So the so
one of these rules has an exception, one rule is not going
to work for everything.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says הא לא קתני. ha lo katani.
So the גמרא's Gemara answer is, which is interesting when the גמרא
Gemara chooses to say this, don't go making inferences. Okay, the משנה
mishna is just coming to tell you the פשט pshat of the
משנה, mishna, not the inference of the reverse case. So assuming now
our משנה mishna reads ראוי לאכילה, rauy l'achila, not ראוי לעבודה, rauy
l'avoda, our משנה mishna reads somebody who's not fit for eating doesn't
get a portion, okay, and that would apply to let's say, you
know, the אונן כהן גדול onen kohen gadol or the טמא קרבנות
ציבור tamei korbanos tzibur etc. Okay, so but do not read it
to say, so that's true, anybody who's not fit for eating doesn't
get a portion. Don't read it to say the reverse, anybody who's
fit for eating gets a portion. Because to say the reverse would
include a קטן katan and that's not true. You with me? So
only read it for what it says, not fit for eating doesn't
get a portion, which does not mean that everybody fit for eating
does because there's a קטן katan that is fit for eating who
doesn't. Okay, but it is true that not fit doesn't get. If
you are fit, most likely you'll get but not necessarily, okay. So
only read it like the surface meaning, don't read it with the
inference meaning. So the גמרא Gemara says השתא דאתית להכי, hasha d'asis
l'hachi, now that you're telling me that, to only read it by
the literal by the by the straight meaning and not by the...
So the גמרא Gemara says השתא דאתית להכי, Hashata dasis lachai, now
that you're telling me that, to only read it by the literal,
by the straight meaning and not by the inference, so לעולם כדאמרי
מעיקרא, le'olam kede'amrei me'ikara, I can go and have it with its
original read, not that it's about eating, it's about עבודה. avoda. Not
fit for the עבודה avoda doesn't get. Now that's true, your question
was you have a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who's an אונן onen
and a and a טמא בקרבנות ציבור, tamei bekorbanos tzibur, they're fit
and they don't get. But we didn't say fit gets, we said
not fit doesn't get. Okay, so not fit doesn't get is not
fit for עבודה avoda doesn't get is true. If you're fit for
the עבודה, avoda, most likely you'll get but not a hundred percent.
Okay, if we're just going to not go by the inference, it's
true. Of course no, it's not true, because by having it have
the עבודה avoda meaning, there is still the contradiction of a בעל
מום, ba'al mum, right? Not fit for עבודה avoda doesn't get is
not true in the case of the בעל מום. ba'al mum. So
that's why we'd rather read it as אכילה achila rather than as
עבודה. avoda. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אי משום טמא, טמא
לא קתני. i mishum tamei, tamei lo kasni. If you say, "Oh,
a טמא בקרבנות ציבור tamei bekorbanos tzibur
is fit and he doesn't get," fine, that's the inference. We're not
going by the inference. We're only going by the פשט. pshat. Not
fit doesn't get. ואי משום בעל מום, ve'i mishum ba'al mum, okay,
but בעל מום ba'al mum contradicts that. רחמנא רבייה. rachmana rabyei. No,
בעל מום ba'al mum is an exception. Fine, the rule is true,
except for the exceptions. Okay, so you basically have, right, the reading
of... it's very funny that the גמרא gemara is forced to say
don't go by the inferences. Okay, so you have the reading of
not fit for
עבודה avoda doesn't get and then you have the not fit for
אכילה. achila. Okay, so not fit for אכילה achila doesn't get. Okay,
so so so who's not fit for אכילה? achila? So that would
be somebody like טמא tamei or whatever, אונן, onen, etc., etc. Okay,
now you have the person about כהן גדול אונן Kohen Gadol onen
and טמא קרבנות ציבור. tamei korbanot tzibur. Okay, and they are
not fit for אכילה achila doesn't get.
They are not fit
and they do get, right?
At least in some cases.
Oh, these do get. They're not fit for אכילה... achila... no, they
don't get. I'm sorry. They're fit for עבודה. avoda. Right. They are
wait. Not fit for אכילה achila because of טמא ציבור, tamei tzibur,
you still eat...
there's one קרבן korban you still eat.
That's true. They're not fit for אכילה achila and they don't get.
That's true.
Except קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
And they don't get. Fine, fine, fine. That's true. Okay, check. So
that works, right? Okay, so the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol that works.
They're not fit for אכילה achila and they don't get. Then you've
got the case of the קטן. katan. Okay, he is fit for
אכילה achila and doesn't get. Okay, but the גמרא gemara. says that
doesn't bother us. We're only we're only saying... that's the... don't infer
the reverse. He does get. Just say not fit doesn't get. Doesn't.
And that is correct. Okay, so not fit doesn't get. That's correct.
Okay, right? That is correct. Fit gets, that we're not talking about.
So you can have somebody... most people who are fit will get.
There is a קטן katan who's fit who doesn't, but that's not
a problem. That's this read. Okay. And the בעל מום ba'al mum
is fit for אכילה, achila, so it's also and he does get,
so that's not a problem at all. Okay. Not fit for עבודה
avoda doesn't get. So who's not fit for עבודה? avoda? טמא, tamei,
אונן, onen etc. Okay, now you have
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, אונן onen, and טמא קרבנות
ציבור. tamei korbanot
tzibur. They are fit for עבודה avoda and they don't get.
Right? Okay, but that's like, okay, but we're talking about not fit.
Don't if they're fit for the עבודה, avoda, you know, somebody who's
fit usually will get. These people are fit, they don't get, but
don't worry about that. We're talking about not fit, so don't ask
me, right, about these two cases. Right? The case of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol אונן onen and טמא בקרבנות ציבור, tamei bekorbanos tzibur,
it's true they're fit and they don't get, but that's the inference.
We're just saying not fit doesn't get. Okay. How about the קטן?
katan? So the קטן katan is not fit and he doesn't get.
Right? So that actually fits our rule. This fits, this
is the inference, we're going to ignore that. Okay, and the בעל
מום, ba'al mum, he is not fit and he gets.
Uh-oh, so there we're going to say, uh-oh,
that is exactly the description here, not fit but he gets, it
says doesn't get. So that we're going to say is an exception.
Okay? So basically, if you read it אכילה achila so then there're
no exceptions. It's just, again, only read the explicit statement, don't read
the inverse. If you read it as עבודה avoda then you have
to accept that the בעל מום baal mum is an exception.
What?
Why doesn't the minor get a portion?
Because based on a פסוק. pasuk. It says
איש כאחיו, ish ke'achiv, which is man. All right. Anyway, so the
bottom line is is that none of these rules work both in
the positive and the negative. Okay? So none of them work both
ways, and if you read it about the עבודה, avoda, then the
בעל מום baal mum is an exception. If you read it about
the אכילה, achila, then the בעל מום baal mum is not an
exception. Okay?
But we didn't decide whether it's עבודה avoda or אכילה. achila.
Right, there's really not one rule that really works for everything. I
mean, the אכילה achila rule works best, but again, it doesn't work
in the reverse. And so maybe so that gets to that question,
do we look at בעל מום baal mum as an exception or
do we look at it fundamentally as not exception? Okay. אפילו מיטמא
בשעת זריקת דמים וטהור בשעת הקטר חלבים אינו חולק. afilu mitama bishat
zrikat damim vatahor bishat haktar chalavim eino cholek.
So the משנה mishna says the key is whether you were טמא
tamei when the blood was being thrown, when it was being made
into a קרבן, korban, that's the key moment to determine even if
you were טהור tahor at the הקטר חלבים haktar chalavim at the
burning of the fat. הטהור בשעת זריקת דמים וטמא בשעת הקטר חלבים.
hatahor bishat zrikat damim vetamei bishat haktar chalavim. So the obvious implication
of the משנה mishna is if that you were טהור tahor when
the blood was being thrown and טמא tamei when the fat was
being burned, and let's say the fat was being burned during the
daytime and then you were טהור tahor again that night, okay, so
the implication is חולק, cholek,
you do get a portion, right? It's all just about the blood.
So as long as you're טהור tahor during the blood we don't
care about the fat. מתניתין דלא כאבא שאול, matnitin delo ke'abba shaul,
it's not like אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. דתניא ותני ברייתא, detanya vetane
baraita, אבא שאול Abba Shaul אומר, omer, לעולם אינו אוכל עד שיהא
טהור משעת זריקה עד שעת הקטר חלבים. le'olam eino ochel ad sheyehe
tahor mishat zrika ad she'at haktar chalavim. You actually have to be
טהור tahor at both stages. It's not just about the blood. It's
not enough to be the fat, but you need both the blood
and the fat in order to be get a portion. דאמר קרא,
da'amar kra, the verse says, המקריב את דם השלמים ואת החלב. hamakriv
et dam hashlamim ve'et hachelev. Right? דאפילו הקטר חלבים נמי
בעי. de'afilu haktar chalavim nami ba'ei. Pretty straight read of the פסוק.
pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says לו תהיה שוק הימין למנה. lo tihiye
shok hayamin lemana. Right? It says that if you do the blood
and the חלב, chelev, so you have to be טהור tahor at
both moments. Hold on one second, let me... I
got a tissue. I have some
right here. Okay, I have, I have.
Okay, so now the גמרא gemara questions according to that the following.
It says איבעיא להו לרב אשי. ibaia lehu lerav ashi. רב אשי
Rav Ashi asked: within this position of אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, נטמא
בינתיים מהו? nitma beintayim mahu?
Let's say the guy was טהור tahor at the דם, dam, became
טמא, tamei, then became טהור tahor again by the הקטר חלבים, haktar
chalavim, which you could have because you became טמא, tamei, you went
to the מקווה, mikvah, you had הערב שמש, ha'erev shemesh, and then
you did the הקטר חלבים haktar chalavim at night. So it actually
can work because הקטר חלבים haktar chalavim is done at night.
So what would the story be for אבא שאול? Abba Shaul? Okay,
so מהו? mahu? בשעת זריקה ובשעת הקטרה בעינן? bishat zrika uvishat haktara
beinun?
You only need those two points ואיכא ve'ika and you have it.
או דלמא עד דאיכא טהרה משעת זריקה ועד שעת הקטר חלבים? o
dilma ad de'ika tahara mishat zrika ve'ad she'at haktar chalavim? Or is
it a sense of for that entire process from the beginning to
the end? תיקו, teiku, we don't know. אמר רבא, amar rava, last
now discussion here, and this is a great little גמרא. Gemara Okay,
אמר רבא, amar rava, I mean the way it sort of frames
this whole discussion, האי דינא דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון גמירנא. hai dina
derabbi eliezer berbi shimon gmirna. The following הלכה halacha I learned or
discussion, not so much a הלכה halacha here but as we'll see
like a קל וחומר kal vachomer דין, din, I learned from רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Eliezer berbi Shimon. דאמרה בבית הכסא דנתא בה.
de'amra beveit hakise danta ba. דנתא, danta,
and he says that he who told me that he sort of
thought this out when he was in the bathroom. Okay? Which is
a pretty interesting thing. The גמרא Gemara is going to ask in
the end since when are you allowed to learn תורה torah in
the bathroom? There's a line in the ירושלמי yerushalmi where one אמורא
amora says 'My best תורה torah I thought of when I was
in the bathroom.' Okay, anyway, so now here's his discussion. So the
whole name of our פרק perek is טבול יום, tvul yom, right?
Our משנה mishna talked about the טבול יום tvul yom and the
מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kipurim and the אונן onen and so on. So
it imagines this discussion of does a טבול יום tvul yom get
a portion as a discussion as if the טבול יום tvul yom
in person was coming to his fellow כהנים kohanim and asking for
a portion. It really personalizes it, okay? Please let me have a
portion, okay? And what it's really coming to do is say that
there are three פסוקים psukim that basically
exclude people that can't do the עבודה avoda from getting a portion.
We'll see: one is by a מנחה, mincha, one is by a
חטאת, chatat, one is by שלמים, shlamim, and it's going to explain
why you need all three פסוקים. psukim. But rather than just sort
of say it, oh you need this to tell you this case
and this to tell you that case, it's going to describe it
in a narrative about this טבול יום tvul yom who's coming and
having a discussion with his fellow כהנים. kohanim. Okay? בא טבול יום,
ba tvul yom, the טבול יום tvul yom comes and אמר and
says to his fellow כהנים: kohanim: תנו לי מן המנחה ואוכל, tenu
li min hamincha ve'ochel, let me have a portion of the מנחה
mincha that I might eat from it. אמר לו, amar lo, so
his כהן kohen friend says to him, brother says to him: ומה
אם במקום שיפה כוחך בחטאתך, uma im bamakom sheyafe kochacha bachatatcha,
look buddy, when it comes to a חטאת chatat where you have
more power. Why do you have more power? Because a כהן kohen
who brings a חטאת chatat or a קרבן korban any time of
the... Here he can eat, he is entitled to eating the meat
of his חטאת chatas whenever he brings it as opposed to it
being divided by the כהנים kohanim of the משמר. mishmar. So that's
a question about entitled to the meat, who זוכה zoche in the
meat. So when it's your own חטאת, chatas, you have a lot
of entitlement, you have a strong position, and nevertheless דחיתני מחטאת ישראל,
dachisani michatas yisrael, we know, because here it's about a מנחה, mincha,
so we're already assuming that the הלכה halacha is that a כהן
kohen does not get a portion in a חטאת chatas when he
is טמא. tamei. Okay, so even in the world of a חטאת
chatas where normally you have more rights, nevertheless when you're טמא tamei
and a ישראל yisrael brings a חטאת, chatas, you don't get a
portion. Okay, so if you don't get a portion in that world
where you have stronger rights when you're טמא, tamei, מקום שהורע כחך,
makom shehura kochecha, now we're in the world of a מנחה mincha
and in a מנחה mincha your entitlement is less, because when you
bring your own במנחתך, beminchatacha, what happens to a מנחה mincha of
a כהן? kohen Anybody know?
You burn it. None of it gets eaten. So in the world
of a מנחה mincha where you have no rights to your own
מנחה, mincha, אינו דין שאדיחך ממנחת ישראל? aino din sheadichacha meminchas yisrael?
How much
more so should I have the right to push you away and
say don't ask me for a portion in this ישראל's yisrael מנחה,
mincha, you were טמא. tamei. Okay, this world of a מנחה mincha
is a world where you have less rights in general, so get
out of here. We know you don't get a portion of a
חטאת, chatas, you don't get a portion of a מנחה. mincha. Okay,
so he says back to him, no, ומה דדחיתני ממנחת ישראל, uma
didachisani miminchas yisrael, you had a right to push me away from
the חטאת, chatas, שכשם שיפה כחי כך יפה כחך, shekeshem sheyafe kochi
kach yafe kochecha,
because yes, I have more rights in the world of חטאת, chatas,
but you also have more rights in the world of חטאת. chatas.
So maybe that's why you were able to push me away, because
your rights were stronger. Okay, but תדיחני ממנחה? tadicheini mimincha? But maybe
in a מנחה mincha world you can't push me away, שכשם שהורע
כחי, shekeshem shehura kochi, the same way my rights are weaker, כך
הורע כחך, kach hura kochecha, your rights are weaker. Okay, so maybe
no, maybe just because you know I don't get a חטאת chatas
when I can't do the עבודה, avoda, maybe I do get a
מנחה, mincha, because all כהנים's kohanim rights in מנחות minchos are weaker,
so maybe we should be more on equal footing. הרי אומר, harei
omer,
so that's why you need a verse to tell me that he
doesn't get even in a מנחה, mincha, והכהן המקריב אותה לו תהיה,
v'hakohen hamakriv osa lo sihye, which is a פסוק pasuk by a
מנחה. mincha. Not only does this apply to a חטאת, chatas, it
even applies to a מנחה. mincha. בוא הקרב ואכול, bo hakrev v'ochal,
and he says, so this כהן kohen says to him, hey, I
got this פסוק, pasuk, you want a portion in the מנחה? mincha?
Let's first see you come ahead and do the עבודה. avoda. You
can't do the עבודה, avoda, you're not going to get a portion.
Okay, now he says fine, so now I'm not going to get
a מנחה, mincha, now he comes back and says give me a
חטאת. chatas. Okay, I mean the previous discussion assumed we knew the
הלכה halacha by חטאת, chatas, but now we're going back to the
חטאת. chatas. תן לי מחטאת ישראל ואוכל. ten li michatas yisrael v'ochal.
Fine, but at least give me a חטאת chatas and I'll eat.
אמר ליה, amar lei, so his fellow כהן kohen? says to him,
ומה במקום שהורע כחך במנחתי, uma b'makom shehura kochecha beminchasi, look, buddy,
if I was able to push you off of the מנחה mincha
even though my rights were weaker in a מנחה, mincha, דחיתני ממנחת
ישראל, dachisani miminchas yisrael,
so even though my rights are weaker in a מנחה mincha I
was able to push you off, מקום שיפה כחי בחטאתי, makom sheyafe
kochi b'chatasi, in a חטאת chatas world where my rights are stronger,
אינו דין שאדיחך מחטאת ישראל? aino din sheadichacha michatas yisrael? I should
of course be able to get rid of you and push you
away. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, ומה שדחיתני
ממנחת ישראל, uma shedachisani miminchas yisrael,
no, no, no, maybe you were entitled to push me away from
a מנחה, mincha, שכשם שהורע כחך כך הורע כחי, shekeshem shehura kochecha
kach hura kochi, because your rights were weaker but my rights were
weaker. So that's why you were able to push me away from
a מנחה. mincha. תדיחני מחטאת ישראל? tadicheini michatas yisrael?
But how says you can push me away from a חטאת? chatas?
שכשם שיפה כחך כך יפה כחי. shekeshem sheyafe kochecha kach yafe kochi.
You have more rights, but I also have more rights by a
חטאת, chatas, so maybe you can't push me away from a חטאת.
chatas. הרי אומר, harei omer, so then the כהן kohen says to
him, no, buddy, the פסוק pasuk says by a חטאת chatas also,
הכהן המחטא אותה יאכלנה. hakohen hamichate osa yochlena. בוא חטא ואכול, bo
chatei v'ochal, go ahead,
let's see you do the עבודה, avoda, then you'll get a portion.
So that's basically saying why you need both by a חטאת chatas
and a מנחה, mincha, but it says it in this very dramatic
narrative of him asking for a portion and being pushed away. אמר
ליה, amar lei, so then he says to him, תן לי מחזה
ושוק ואוכל. ten li mechaze v'shok v'ochal. Fine, give me the חזה
chaze and the שוק shok of a שלמים, shelamim, because that's a
third פסוק. pasuk. That's a third פסוק, pasuk, it's telling us why
you need all three פסוקים. pesukim. Okay, give me חזה chaze and
שוק. shok. Why? אמר ליה, amar lei, so his fellow כהן kohen
says to him, ומה במקום שיפה כחך בחטאת, uma b'makom sheyafe kochecha
b'chatas, I don't get it, דחיתני, dachisani, if I was able to
push you away from a חטאת chatas where you have more rights,
דחיתני מחטאת ישראל, dachisani michatas yisrael, so מקום שהורע כחך בשלמים, makom
shehura kochecha b'shlamim, by שלמים shelamim you have fewer rights, right, because
why do you have fewer rights? Because the ישראל yisrael gets most
of the meat, שאין לך בהן אלא חזה ושוק, she'ein lecha bahen
ela chaze v'shok, you only get the the the breast and the
thigh, אינו דין שאדיחך? aino din sheadichacha? How much more so should
I be able to push you away. Okay, so he says, nobody,
like if I can push you away from a חטאת, chatas, I
can certainly push you away from this. So he says back to
him, no, מה דדחיתני מחטאת, ma didachisani michatas, maybe you pushed me
away from a חטאת, chatas, שכן הורע כחי אצל נשי ועבדי, sheken
hura kochi etzel nishai v'avadai,
by a חטאת chatas my rights are weaker. Why are my rights
weaker? In the portion and my family. And that even in the
portion that I get, I can't give it to my wife and
my slaves. Okay? Whereas in a שלמים, Shlamim, even though I get
less, I actually have more rights in what I get. Okay? But
ותדחיני מחדא ושב שכן יפה כוחי אצל נשיי ועבדיי, ve-tadicheini mi-chada ve-shav
she-ken yafeh kochi etzel nashi ve-avadai, I can give it to my
wife and to my slaves. Okay? So I'm sorry, I have more
rights in a שלמים Shlamim in the portion I'm entitled to and
maybe I should be therefore getting it even though I can't do
the עבודה. avoda. הרי אומר, harei omer, so he says back to
him, לכהן המזרק את דם השלמים לו יהיה. la-kohein ha-mazrek es dam
ha-shlamim lo yihyeh. No, sorry, we got a third פסוק. pasuk. בו
זרוק ואכול, bo zerok ve-echol, if you can do the דם, dam,
then you can get a portion. So he tried all these ways
to get a portion in something and he kept on pushing him
away. So יצא, yatza, this is so poignant, יצא טבול יום, yatza
tvul yom, so the טבול יום tvul yom walks away sort of
like, you know, you know, like, you know, despondent, קל וחומר על
ראשו, kal va-chomer al rosho, all of his קל וחומרs kal va-chomer
piled on his head, okay? אונן מימינו, onein mi-yimino, מחוסר כיפורים משמאלו,
mechusar kippurim mi-smolo, the אונן onein on his right hand, the מחוסר
כיפורים mechusar kippurim on his left hand, they're all walking away, you
can see them, dejected and despondent, they tried and they did not
succeed. Now, we're so I want I'll get back and say something
about that little ending and that narrative, but first one more one
more possible קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. פרך רב אחאי. parach Rav Achai.
רב אחאי Rav Achai asked, wait, there's another thing he could have
said and we're going to deal with a fourth okay, לימרה ליה
תן לי מביכור ואוכל. leimaley ten li mi-bechor ve-ochal. Give me the
בכור bechor and I'll eat. Now this is a little bit funny
because as רש"י Rashi says, a בכור bechor isn't divided by the
כהנים, kohanim, you give your בכור bechor to a כהן kohen you
want to give it to. Okay, so this whole this whole question
is a little is a little funny. But, anyway, משום דאמרי ליה
מה מקום שיפה כוחי בחטאת אצל נשיי ועבדיי דחיתיך
מחטאת ישראל. mishum de-amri lei mah makom she-yafeh kochi be-chatas etzel nashi
ve-avadai de-chiticha mi-chatas Yisrael. Look, if I could push you away from
a חטאת chatas where I have weak rights, says the כהן kohen
his brother, so מקום שיפה כוחי בבכור דכולי דידי, makom she-yafeh kochi
be-bechor de-chulo dilei, where in a בכור bechor where I have more
rights that it's all mine, okay, אינו דין שאדיחך הימני, eino din
she-adichecha mimeni, how much more so should I be able to push
you away? And then he can say back, ומה אם דחיתני מחטאת
שכשם שרע כוחך כך רע כוחי. u-mah im dechitani mi-chatas she-ke-shem she-ra
kochecha kach ra kochi. No, you could push me away from a
חטאת chatas because fine, your rights were weaker, but my rights were
weaker. תדיחני מבכור שכשם שיפה כוחך כך יפה כוחי, tadicheini mi-bechor she-ke-shem
she-yafeh kochecha kach yafeh kochi, my rights are stronger there as well.
הרי אומר את דמם תזרוק על המזבח ואת חלבם תקטיר ובשרם יהיה
לך. harei omer es damam tizrok al hamizbeach ve-es chelbam taktir u-vesaram
yihyeh lach. בו זרוק ואכול. bo zerok ve-echol. Come and throw the
blood and eat. Now this is obviously a very curious and bizarre
because again here it's not really you give it to a כהן
kohein and it's not about dividing it and the whole thing doesn't
make sense. So first of all there's a fascinating תוספות. Tosafos. If
you look at תוספות Tosafos פרך רב אחאי, parach Rav Achai, תוספות
Tosafos says בכל מקום לשונא משונא. be-chol makom leshona meshuna. In all
every time it says פרך רב אחאי parach Rav Achai or whatever,
it's always like a little bit strange what he's asking. כי הא
דריש כתובות פשיט רב אחאי פריך רב אחאי, ke-acha de-reish Kesuvos pashit
Rav Achai parich Rav Achai, ומתוך כך אמר רבנו שמואל דרב אחאי
שעשה שאילתות u-mitoch kach omer Rabbeinu Shmuel de-Rav Achai she-asah she-iltos שאמרו
רבנן סבוראי דבתר רבינא ורב אשי. she-amru Rabbanan Savorai de-basar Ravina ve-Rav
Ashi. This was רב אחאי גאון. Rav Achai Gaon. This is fascinating.
A theory תוספות Tosafos has because רב אחאי Rav Achai always comes
at the end of a סוגיא sugya and asks some like it's
very funny as תוספות Tosafos says like the way he asks some
question at the end of a סוגיא sugya that doesn't let up
and that whatever, it's a little bit off. And תוספות Tosafos says,
you know what? This might be just a gloss that was inserted
after the גמרא Gemara from רב אחאי גאון, Rav Achai Gaon, okay?
But then he doesn't but then תוספות Tosafos says וכתבו אחרי כן
דבריו, ve-kasvu acharei kein devarav, so maybe it was written in the
margin and then it was inserted בסוף הש"ס. be-sof ha-shas. מיהו בהא
דכתובות אשכח רב אשי דמרי בתריה, mihu be-ha de-Kesuvos ashchach Rav Ashi
de-mari basrei, but in כתובות Kesuvos it doesn't sound that way because
רב אשי Rav Ashi is responding to it. So it's an interesting
sort of tech academic point that תוספות Tosafos notes that רב אחאי
Rav Achai gets sometimes introduced at the end of a סוגיא sugya
and it sounds a little off and maybe it's actually the רבנן
סבוראי. Rabbanan Savorai. Anyway, now the גמרא Gemara wraps up this whole
discussion with the אונן onein and the טבול יום tvul yom walking
out dejected with their קל וחומרs kal va-chomer piled on their head.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, והיכי עביד הכי, ve-heichi avid
hachi, one minute, how did רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar think about this
in the bathroom? ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן בכל
מקום מותר להרהר חוץ ממרחץ ומבית הכיסא. ve-amar Rabbah bar bar Chana
amar Rabbi Yochanan be-chol makom mutar leharhir chutz mi-merchatz u-mi-beis ha-kisei. You're
allowed to think in Torah in every place except in the bathhouse
and the bathroom. So the גמרא's answer is לאונסו שאני. le-onsho shani.
If you can't control it, you can't control it. And sometimes your
head is so much in Torah even in the bathroom. So when
we learned this seven years ago, the I you know, I wrote
up a piece about this because I think that it's beautiful that
you know all this time we are being very impersonal, right? All
this time we're just saying, oh this guy doesn't get, this guy
doesn't get, the בעל מום ba'al mum does get, and like you
know we're not thinking about the human sort of drama and the
sense of entitlement and exclusion. So the גמרא very much in this
story really personalizes us, makes us feel what does it mean to
be excluded. And it does it by sort of saying like this
guy's asking and you're being pushed away, pushed away, and he leaves
dejected, like you know that sense of being pushed out, rejected, excluded.
It's not just, oh okay, I'm not going to get a portion.
There's a sense of, you know, of of exclusion and and of
being pushed out, right? And what I think of the bathroom sort
of story is is that like it's the opposite about the bathroom
because the bathroom is a place where you would think you're supposed
to be pushing out Torah, like keeping Torah out, right? You know,
and this and nevertheless like if Torah invades even in the bathroom,
right? Then it's actually even becomes the— Like legitimate, you're not held
responsible, and actually you get to teach over even the תורה Torah
that you learned in the bathroom. Say it was taught in the
bathroom. So it's like the difference between תורה Torah and like קרבנות.
Korbanot. קרבנות Korbanot is all about, you know, limited geographical space, who
gets to go in, who's included, who's excluded, people are kept away,
people are pushed out, right? Whereas תורה, Torah, תורה Torah like forces
itself everywhere. It even forces itself into the bathroom, you know? So
תורה Torah is much more sort of universal, doesn't keep, no place
is free from תורה, Torah, nobody gets sort of pushed out. So
I think like there's a very important point that this is all
being framed, you know, around the fact that it was תורה Torah
that came to him when he was in the bathroom. Okay, we
all...